We've become bored with watching actors give us phony emotions.
On s'est lassés de voir des acteurs simuler des émotions.
We're tired of pyrotechnics and special effects.
On en a assez de la pyrotechnie et des effets spéciaux.
While the world he inhabits is, in some respects, counterfeit,
Si le monde dans lequel il vit est, à certains égards, factice,
there's nothing fake about Truman himself.
Truman, lui, ne fait pas semblant.
No scripts, no cue cards.
Pas de scénario, pas de fiches.
It isn't always Shakespeare, but it's genuine.
Ce n'est pas du Shakespeare, mais c'est authentique.
It's a life.
C'est une vie.
I'm not going to make it.
Je n'y arriverai pas.
You're going to have to go on without me.
Vous continuerez sans moi.
No way, mister.
Pas question.
You're going to the top of this mountain, broken legs and all.
Tu vas gravir cette montagne avec tes jambes cassées.
We find many viewers leave him on all night for comfort.
Certains spectateurs ne l'éteignent pas de la nuit.
You're crazy, you know that?
Vous étes fous.
For me, there is no difference between a private life and a public life.
Je ne fais pas de différence entre vie privée et vie publique.
My life, is my life, is The Truman Show.
Ma vie, c'est le Truman Show.
The Truman Show is a lifestyle.
C'est un style de vie,
It's a noble life. It is
une vie digne. C'est...
a truly blessed life.
une vie bénie.
Yeah, tell me something I don't know.
Donne-leur du nouveau.
All right. Promise me one thing, though.
Bon, mais promettez-moi une chose:
If I die before I reach the summit,
Si je meurs avant d'avoir atteint le sommet,
you'll use me as an alternative source of food.
vous m'utiliserez comme nourriture.
Gross.
Tu es dégoùtant!
It's all true. It's all real.
Tout est vrai. Tout est réel.
Nothing here is fake. Nothing you see on this show is fake.
Rien n'est truqué. Il n'y a aucun truquage.
It's merely controlled.
C'est juste contrôlé.
Eat me, damn it. That's an order.
Mangez-moi, nom de Dieu! C'est un ordre.
Maybe just your love handles.
Tes poignées d'amour, à la rigueur.
I have love handles? Yeah. Little ones.
J'ai des poignées d'amour? Oui. Des petites.
Truman. You're going to be late.
Truman! Tu vas étre en retard.
Okay!
J'arrive!
- Good morning. - Morning.
- Bonjour!
Good morning.
Bonjour.
In case I don't see you, good afternoon, good evening, and good night.
Et au cas où je ne vous reverrais pas,
Yeah.
Oui.
- Morning, Truman. - Morning, Spencer.
- Bonjour, Truman. - Bonjour, Spencer.
Hey, Pluto. No, get down.
Salut, Pluto. Va-t'en.
- He won't hurt you. - Get down.
- Il ne mord pas. - Va-t'en.
I know.
Je sais.
- It's just me. - Come on, Pluto.
- C'est moi. - Viens, Pluto.
What is it?
Qu'est-ce que c'est?
Here's a news flash just in. An aircraft in trouble began shedding parts
Flash d'information: Un avion en difficulté a perdu quelques piéces
as it flew over Seahaven just a few moments ago.
au-dessus de Seahaven il y a quelques instants.
Luckily, no one was hurt.
Heureusement, pas de blessés.
But, hey, how do you feel today?
Et vous, ça va?
That's good. You thinking of flying somewhere?
Vous envisagez de prendre l'avion?
- Nope. - No? Good.
- Non. - Bien!
This is Classical Clive with Classical Drive
Vous êcoutez Classical Clive.
so why don't you forget about the perils of flying,
Oublions les dangers de l'aêronautique
settle back, and let this music calm you down?
et laissons-nous bercer par cette musique.
- Dog Fancy, please. - Dog Fancy.
- Luxes de chien, s'il vous plaît. - Luxes de chien.
- Thank you very much.
- Merci beaucoup. - C'est moi.
Give me a paper there, will you, Earl?
Le journal, Earl.
And one of these for the wife.
Et celui-là, pour ma femme.
Loves her fashion mags.
Elle adore les magazines.
Will that be all for you, Truman?
C'est tout, Truman?
- That's the whole kit and caboodle. - Catch you later.
- C'est tout le toutim! - A plus.
Okay. Yeah.
Ca marche.
Good morning.
Bonjour.
- Hank. - Morning, Truman.
- Hank. - Bonjour, Truman.
- Good morning, Truman. - How are you guys?
- Comment ça va?
- Beautiful day, isn't it? - Always.
- Beau temps, hein? - Toujours!
And how's your lovely wife?
Comment va ta ravissante épouse?
Good. How about yours?
Bien. Et les vôtres?
- Couldn't be better. - Fine.
- On ne peut mieux. - Bien.
- Nice talking to you, Truman. - You, too.
- Ravis. - De méme.
We must go now.
On doit y aller.
Think about that policy. Okay, that's two for one. That's a good deal.
Réfléchissez, pour vos polices. Deux contrats pour le prix d'un.
- Doppelgänger special. - Right.
- Spécial doublon. - D'accord.
Hi.
Salut.
Hey, fellows. You going in? Go ahead.
Je vous en prie.
- Go ahead. - No, you first, please.
- Allez-y. - Aprés vous.
I'm not that anxious to get there.
Je ne suis pas si pressé d'y retourner.
Yes, hello.
Bonjour.
Could I have directory assistance for Fiji, please? Fiji islands.
Je cherche un numéro aux Fidji. Les Fidji.
Truman, did you see this?
Truman, t'as vu ça?
I'm sorry, ma'am.
Pardon.
If he's in a coma, he's probably uninsurable.
S'il est dans le coma, il est inassurable.
Hello? Yes. Fiji, please.
Oui, les Fidji.
Do you have a listing for Lauren Garland?
Auriez-vous le numéro de Lauren Garland?
Nothing listed?
Rien à ce nom.
Okay. Do you have a Sylvia Garland?
Et une certaine Sylvia Garland?
"S" for Sylvia.
S comme Sylvia.
Nothing?
Rien.
Okay. Thank you.
D'accord. Merci.
- Lawrence. - Hey, Burbank.
- Lawrence! - Salut, Burbank.
Got a prospect in Wells Park I need you to close.
J'ai un client éventuel à Wells Park pour toi.
Wells Park?
Wells Park?
- On Harbor Island? - You know another one?
- Sur l'île de Harbor? - Tu en connais une autre?
I can't do it. I have an appointment. Dentist.
Je ne peux pas. J'ai rendez-vous. Dentiste.
You're going to lose a lot more than your teeth if you don't meet your quota.
Tu risques pire que de perdre tes dents.
Look, Truman,
Ecoute, Truman.
they're making cutbacks at the end of this month.
Ils dégraissent, en fin de mois.
- Cutbacks? - Yeah. Now, you need this.
- Ils dégraissent? - Il te faut ce client.
Besides, a half-hour across the bay, a little sea air would do you good.
Une petite traversée, l'air de la mer, ça te fera du bien.
Thanks.
Merci.
Hello.
Bonjour.
Ferry's still here. Thought I might have missed it.
Le ferry est encore à quai? Je pensais l'avoir raté.
One-way or return?
Un aller?
Return.
Et retour.
There you go, sir.
Voilà, monsieur.
- Do you need any help, sir? - You go ahead. I'll be fine.
- Besoin d'aide? - Allez-y. Tout va bien.
Yeah.
Oui.
Hi, honey.
Chéri!
Look what I got free at the checkout.
J'ai eu un cadeau aux caisses.
It's a Chef's Pal. It's a dicer, grater, peeler, all in one.
Pour découper, râper et éplucher.
Never needs sharpening, dishwasher-safe.
Sans affùtage, lavable en machine.
Wow!
Ouah!
That's amazing.
Epatant!
Truman,
Truman.
you missed a spot.
Tu en as laissé.
That is a beer.
Ca, c'est de la biére.
You know, I'm thinking about getting out, Marlon.
J'ai envie de partir, Marlon.
Yeah? Out of what?
D'où?
Out of my job, out of Seahaven.
De mon boulot, de Seahaven,
- Off this island. Out. - Out of your job?
- de cette île. - Ton boulot?
What the hell's wrong with your job? You have a great job, Truman.
Pourquoi? Tu as un super boulot.
You have a desk job. I'd kill for a desk job.
Un emploi de bureau! Si j'en avais un!
Here you go.
Tiens.
You should try stocking vending machines for a living.
Essaie de garnir des distributeurs...
- No, thanks. - Now there's excitement.
- Sans façon. - Si tu crois que c'est mieux.
Don't you ever get antsy? Itchy feet?
Tu n'as jamais de fourmis dans les pieds?
Where's there to go?
Où aller?
Fiji.
Aux Fidji.
Where the hell's Fiji? Near Florida?
C'est où? Prés de la Floride?
- See here? - Yeah.
- Regarde. - Oui.
This is us,
Là, c'est nous...
and all the way around here,
et complétement de l'autre côté...
Fiji.
les Fidji.
You can't get any further away before you start coming back.
Impossible d'aller plus loin sans commencer à revenir.
You know, there are still islands in Fiji
Il y a des îles, aux Fidji,
where no human being has ever set foot.
où personne n'a jamais mis les pieds.
So when are you going to go?
Tu pars quand?
It's not that simple.
Ce n'est pas si simple.
It takes money,
Ca demande de l'argent,
planning.
du temps.
I can't just up and go.
Je ne peux pas partir comme ça.
Right.
C'est vrai.
I'm going to do it. Don't worry about that.
Je le ferai, ne t'inquiéte pas.
Bonus time is just around the corner.
La chance attend au coin de la rue.
- You coming for a drink? - No, I can't tonight.
- Tu viens prendre un verre? - Je ne peux pas ce soir.
I don't like the look of that weather, son. I think we should head back.
Le temps ne me dit rien qui vaille. Rentrons.
- No, Dad. Not yet. - No, come on. We should go back.
- Encore un peu plus loin, s'il te plaît! - Non.
- A bit farther, please? - Son, listen.
- Allez. - Ecoute.
- Okay. - Yes.
- D'accord. - Oui!
Daddy!
Papa!
You're soaked. Where have you been?
Tu es trempé! D'où viens-tu?
I figure we can scrape together $8,000...
On peut réunir 8000 dollars...
Every time you and Marlon get together...
Quand tu vois Marlon...
We can bum around the world for a year on that.
De quoi bourlinguer un an!
And then what, Truman? We'd be where we were five years ago.
Pour se retrouver au méme point qu'il y a cinq ans?
- You're talking like a teenager. - Maybe I feel like a teenager.
- Tu parles comme un ado. - Je me sens comme un ado.
We have mortgage payments, Truman.
On a des traites à payer.
We have car payments.
La voiture à rembourser.
What, we're just going to walk away from our financial obligations?
Tu veux que nous fuyions nos responsabilités?
It would be an adventure.
Ce serait l'aventure!
I thought we were going to try for a baby. Isn't that enough of an adventure?
On a parlé de faire un enfant. Ca ne suffit pas comme aventure?
That can wait. I want to get away.
Ca peut attendre. Je veux partir.
See some of the world, explore.
Voir le monde! Explorer!
Honey, you want to be an explorer?
Tu veux étre explorateur?
This'll pass.
Ca te passera.
We all think like this now and then.
On a tous nos lubies.
Let's get you out of these wet clothes,
Quitte ces vétements trempés.
come to bed.
Viens te coucher.
You never see anything anyway. They always
On ne voit jamais rien.
turn the camera and play music and,
Ils tournent la caméra, ils envoient la musique,
you know, the wind blows in, and the curtains move
le vent se léve, les rideaux bougent.
and you don't see anything.
On voit rien.
- Dog Fancy, please. - Dog Fancy.
- Luxes de chien, s'il vous plaît. - Luxes de chien.
Thank you.
Merci.
- Paper, Earl, please. - Paper.
- Le journal, Earl. - Le journal.
I might as well pick one of these up while I'm at it.
Et pendant que j'y suis.
- For the wife? - She's got to have them.
- Pour madame. - Il les lui faut tous.
- Anything else, Truman? - That's the whole ball of wax.
- C'est tout? - C'est tout le saint-frusquin.
- Catch you later. - Okay.
- A plus. - Salut.
Dad?
Papa?
What are you doing?
Que faites-vous?
What the... Get out of the way!
Poussez-vous!
Stop them!
Arrétez-les!
Stop those people!
Arrétez ces gens!
Open the doors! Somebody, stop the bus!
Ouvrez la porte! Arrétez le bus!
Stop the bus! Somebody, stop it!
Arrétez ce bus!
And wasn't it funny...
C'était marrant...
It doesn't sound insane at all, Truman.
C'est tout à fait normal, Truman.
I see him 10 times a week in 100 different faces.
Moi, je le vois dix fois par semaine, sous différents traits.
I almost hugged a perfect stranger in the salon last Thursday.
J'ai failli embrasser un inconnu, jeudi, au salon de coiffure!
It was Dad. I swear. Dressed like a homeless man.
C'était papa! Je te jure! Habillé en clochard.
And you know what else was strange?
Et, autre bizarrerie,
A businessman and a woman with a little dog
un couple avec un chien
came out of nowhere and forced him onto a bus.
l'a fait monter de force dans un bus!
It's about time they cleaned up the trash downtown
II est temps de nettoyer cette ville
before we become just like the rest of the country.
avant qu'elle ne ressemble aux autres!
They never found Dad's body. Maybe somehow...
On n'a jamais retrouvé son corps, peut-étre que...
God!
Bon sang!
I'm telling you, if it wasn't him, it was his twin.
Si ce n'était pas lui, c'était son jumeau!
- Did Dad have a brother? - Truman, you know perfectly well
- Papa avait un frére? - Tu sais bien
that your father was an only child, just like you.
que ton pére était fils unique comme toi.
Now, sweetie,
Mon chéri,
you're just feeling bad because of what happened.
tu es perturbé à cause de ce qui s'est passé.
You, sailing off into that storm.
Naviguer sous un orage!
But I've never blamed you, Truman,
Je ne te l'ai jamais reproché.
and I don't blame you now.
Je ne te reproche rien.
Truman?
Truman?
What are you doing down here?
Qu'est-ce que tu fais?
Fixing the mower.
Je bricole.
- Saw my father today. - I know.
- J'ai vu mon pére aujourd'hui. - Je sais.
Your mother called.
Ta mére a appelé.
You really shouldn't upset her like that.
Tu devrais la ménager.
Did you want... What did you want?
Que voulais-tu?
I made macaroni.
J'ai fait des macaronis.
I'm not hungry.
Je n'ai pas faim.
You know, you really ought to throw out that mower.
On devrait changer cette tondeuse
Get one of those new Elk Rotaries.
pour un modéle Elk Rotaries.
What's he doing?
Qu'est-ce qu'il fait?
See, they got rid of her, but they couldn't erase the memory.
Lls l'ont éliminée, mais pas son souvenir.
The memory of who?
Le souvenir de qui?
- You okay? You all right? - Excuse me. Hi.
- Ca va? - Excuse-moi.
- Hi. - I'm so sorry I fell on you like that.
- Salut. - Je suis désolée!
- It's okay. - I've just been such a klutz all day.
- C'est rien. - Je suis maladroite aujourd'hui!
It's all right.
T'en fais pas.
Sprained this ankle. Oh, my goodness. I'm so sorry.
J'ai dù me fouler la cheville. Désolée
- I'm so sorry to fall on you like that. - That's all right. Don't worry about it.
- de t'étre tombée dessus comme ça. - C'est pas grave.
- I'm Meryl. - Hi, I'm Truman.
- Meryl. - Truman.
Hey, nice to meet you.
Enchantée.
- Truman, you've studied enough. - No. I got to commit this to memory.
- Tu as assez révisé. - Il faut que je mémorise ça.
Come on, Truman, one ice-cold brewski.
Une petite mousse bien fraîche!
Come on.
Allez.
You're going to have to copy off me, so be careful.
Tu seras obligé de copier sur moi.
You're a better person than I am.
Tu es plus sérieux que moi.
- See you later. - Okay.
- A tout à l'heure. - Oui.
- Bye.
- Salut.
See you later, loser.
A plus, minable.
Hi.
Salut.
- Konnichi-wa. - What?
- Konnichi-wa. - Quoi?
You take Japanese.
Tu fais du japonais?
Yes.
Oui.
Lauren, right?
Lauren, c'est ça?
It's on the...
C'est sur...
Lauren. Right.
Lauren. Oui.
I'm Truman Burbank.
Truman Burbank.
Yeah, I know.
Je sais.
You know, Truman, I'm not allowed to talk to you.
Je n'ai pas le droit de te parler.
Really?
Ah bon?
Yeah. I can understand that. I'm a pretty dangerous character.
Je suis dangereux, c'est vrai.
I'm sorry. It's not up to me.
Ca ne dépend pas de moi.
A girl's got to be careful.
Une fille doit se méfier.
- You have a boyfriend, right? - No, it's not that.
- Tu as un copain. - Ce n'est pas ça.
Was it Meryl, that girl that was with me? We're not... We don't...
C'est à cause de Meryl?
We're just friends.
C'est juste une amie.
- It's nothing like that. - It's how I look?
- Il ne s'agit pas de ça. - C'est moi?
Not your type?
Je suis pas ton genre?
No.
Non.
I like your pin.
COMMENT CA VA FINIR?
I was wondering that myself.
Moi aussi, je me demande comment ça va finir.
Would you want to maybe, possibly,
Accepterais-tu
sometime go out for some pizza or something?
de sortir manger une pizza
Like, Friday?
vendredi?
- Saturday? - I can't.
- Samedi? - Je ne peux pas.
Sunday, Monday, Tuesday?
Dimanche, lundi, mardi?
- We have finals tomorrow. - Yeah, I know.
- On doit réviser! - Je sais.
If we don't go now, it won't happen.
C'est maintenant ou jamais.
Do you understand? So what do you want to do?
Tu comprends? Alors, que décides-tu?
Please keep your hands inside the car!
II est dangereux de se pencher au-dehors!
This is my favorite pizza place.
Ma pizzeria préférée.
Tony!
Tony!
One large, extra plankton.
Une géante au plancton!
We have so little time. They're going to be here any minute.
On a trés peu de temps. Ils vont arriver.
- Who are? - They don't want me talking to you.
- Qui? - Je ne dois pas te parler.
Then don't talk.
Ne parle pas.
They're here.
Les voilà!
- Truman. - What do they want?
- Truman. - Que veulent-ils?
Listen to me. Everybody knows about you.
Tout le monde sait tout de toi.
Everybody knows everything you do.
Tout le monde sait ce que tu fais.
They're pretending, Truman. Do you understand?
Ils font semblant. Tu comprends?
- Everybody's pretending. - I don't know.
- On fait tous semblant! - Je sais pas.
No, my name's not Lauren. It's Sylvia.
Je ne m'appelle pas Lauren,
- My name's Sylvia. - Sylvia?
- je m'appelle Sylvia! - Sylvia?
- Yeah. - Lauren, sweetheart, not again.
- Oui. - Lauren, chérie, tu recommences?
- Wait a minute. Who are you? - I'm her father.
- Qui étes-vous? - Son pére.
- I've never even seen him before. - We weren't doing anything.
- Je ne l'ai jamais vu! - On ne faisait rien.
He's lying. Truman, please don't listen to him.
Il ment. Truman, ne l'écoute pas!
Everything I've told you is the truth. This, it's fake. It's all for you.
Je t'ai dit la vérité! C'est du faux! C'est pour toi!
- I don't understand. - The sky and sea, everything, it's a set.
- Je ne comprends pas. - Tout ça, c'est un décor!
It's a show.
Une émission.
Everybody's watching you. Please don't listen to him.
Tout le monde te regarde. Ne l'écoute pas!
He's going to lie to you. They're watching us now.
II va te mentir! On nous regarde.
- I want to know what's going on. - Schizophrenia. She has episodes.
- Que se passe-t-il? - Schizophrénie. Elle a des crises.
We've tried everything.
On a tout essayé.
Hypnotism, shock therapy. Don't worry.
Hypnose, thérapies. Ne vous inquiétez pas.
- Truman! - You're not the first.
- Truman! - Vous n'étes pas le premier.
You're not the first. She brings all her boyfriends down here.
Elle les améne tous ici.
What's he saying? Truman, he's lying.
Que dit-il? II ment!
- Get out of here. Come and find me. - Don't worry.
- Evade-toi! Viens me retrouver. - Ne craignez rien.
We're going to Fiji. Fiji. We're moving to Fiji.
On part aux Fidji.
Fiji?
Aux Fidji?
Sylvia!
Sylvia!
Hey!
Hé!
Why didn't he just follow her to Fiji?
Pourquoi il l'a pas suivie aux Fidji?
His mother got sick, really sick. He couldn't leave her. He's kind.
Sa mére est tombée malade. Il pouvait pas la laisser. Il est gentil.
Maybe he's too kind.
Trop gentil.
I can't believe he married Meryl on the rebound.
Je comprends pas qu'il ait épousé Meryl!
Excuse me.
Pardon.
Come on, Sal.
Allons, Sal.
We've already got this on the greatest hits tape.
On a cette scéne sur la cassette des meilleurs extraits.
Can I borrow that?
Tu me la préteras?
Close, but no cigar.
C'est presque ça.
And it's another beautiful day in paradise, folks,
Encore une radieuse journée.
but don't forget to buckle up out there in radio land.
N'oubliez pas votre ceinture.
Remember, a good driver...
N'oubliez pas, un bon conducteur...
...wait for the cue.
...attendez le signal.
Stand by, one.
Camêra 1.
Countdown to action.
Compte à rebours.
He's heading west on Stewart. Stand by, all extras.
Il se dirige vers Stewart. Figurants, tenez-vous prêts.
He'll be on you in about 90 seconds. Props, make sure the coffee's hot.
Il sera sur vous d'ici une minute trente. Assurez-vous que tout est en place.
Okay, he's making his turn onto Lancaster Square.
Il tourne sur Lancaster Square.
Oh, my God! He nearly hit her.
Il a failli l'écraser!
Something's wrong. Change frequencies.
II y a un probléme. On change de frêquence.
Sorry about that, folks.
Pardon.
I guess we picked up a police frequency or something.
Une intertêrence avec la police.
It sometimes happens, and it can drive you crazy.
Ca arrive quelquefois. C'est ênervant.
Okay, it's Classical Clive back in here
Classical Clive est de retour au micro
and we've still got some great music up ahead,
avec de la bonne musique.
but don't forget to buckle up.
Bouclez votre ceinture.
Remember safety. A good driver is a safe driver.
Sécurité, d'abord. Un bon conducteur
A safe driver is what? Yes...
est un conducteur prudent!
Morning, ma'am.
Bonjour, madame.
- I love that idea. - It's pretty cool, isn't it?
- J'adore cette idée. - C'est pas mal, hein?
Can I help?
Je peux vous aider?
Yeah. I have an appointment at Gable Enterprises.
J'ai rendez-vous chez Gable Enterprises.
They went bust.
Ils ont fait faillite.
- What's happening? - Nothing.
- C'est quoi? - Rien.
- Just tell me what's happening. - Got to go, sir. We're remodeling.
- Que se passe-t-il? - On est en travaux.
No, you're not. What are those people doing?
Non. Qui étaient ces gens?
It's none of your business!
Ca ne vous regarde pas.
If you don't tell me what's happening, I'll report you!
Si vous ne m'expliquez pas, je me plaindrai!
You're trespassing.
Vous n'avez rien à faire ici.
Marlon.
Marlon.
- Truman. What are you doing here? - I got to talk to you.
- Qu'est-ce que tu fais là? - Faut que je te parle.
It's a bad time, okay? I'm way behind.
C'est pas le moment.
I'm onto something, Marlon. Something big.
Je suis sur quelque chose d'énorme!
- You okay? You look like shit. - I think I'm mixed up in something.
- Tu as l'air en vrac! - Je suis embarqué dans un truc.
Mixed up in what?
Quoi?
There's no point trying to explain it,
Je peux pas t'expliquer
but a lot of strange things have been happening.
mais il se passe des choses étranges.
The people on the elevator. There was no backing on it.
Les gens dans l'ascenseur. Il n'y avait pas de fond!
I looked out. There was people there.
J'ai vu des gens derriére.
And on the radio on the way to work, it starts following me along,
Et à la radio, ils se sont mis à me suivre!
talking about everything that I'm doing.
A commenter ce que je faisais!
- Know what I mean? - Truman, this is one of your fantasies...
- Tu comprends? - Si c'est ton délire...
I think this is about my dad.
C'est à cause de mon pére.
- Your dad? - I think he's alive.
- Ton pére? - Je crois qu'il est vivant.
Yeah. I'll tell you about it later. I'm definitely being followed.
Je t'expliquerai. Je suis suivi.
Who?
Qui?
It's hard to tell. They look just like regular people.
Difficile à dire. Rien ne les distingue des autres.
- How about those two? - I don't know. Could be.
- Ces deux-là? - Je sais pas. Possible.
It's when I'm unpredictable, that's... They can't, you know.
Quand je fais un truc pas prévu... Ils peuvent pas...
- Did anything happen? - No.
- Ca a eu un effet? - Non.
We gotta get out of here. You ready to go?
Partons. Tu es prét?
- No. I just came here. - Come on.
- Je peux pas. - Allez.
I told you I can't.
Je peux pas.
You're going to get both our asses fired, you know that?
Tu vas nous faire virer.
- Okay, man, let's do it. - What?
- D'accord. Allons-y! - Quoi?
Whatever you say, I'm game.
Je suis partant!
- What are you talking about? - Yes, sirree.
- Qu'est-ce que tu racontes? - Oui, mon cher.
Your birthday comes but once a year.
C'est pas tous les jours ton anniversaire!
Maybe I'm being set up for something.
Je suis peut-étre manipulé.
You ever think about that, Marlon?
Tu ne t'es jamais dit
Like your whole life has been building toward something?
que ta vie n'était peut-étre qu'une manipulation?
No.
Non.
When you were hauling chickens in the summer for Kaiser,
Quand tu transportais des poulets,
what was the furthest you ever got off the island?
jusqu'où es-tu allé, le plus loin d'ici?
Went all over. Never found a place like this, though.
Je suis allé partout. Rien ne vaut notre île.
Look at that sunset, Truman. It's perfect.
Regarde ce coucher de soleil. Une perfection.
Yeah.
Oui.
That's the big guy.
C'est le Grand Manitou.
- Quite a paintbrush he's got. - Yep.
- Il a un sacré coup de pinceau. - Oui.
Just between you and me, Marlon,
Entre nous, Marlon,
I'm going away for a while.
je vais partir quelque temps.
- Really? - Yeah.
- Ah oui? - Oui.
Little angel.
Le petit ange.
My little clown.
Mon petit clown.
Old carrot top.
Poil de carotte.
The best of both of us.
Les meilleures photos.
We should be getting you home, Mother.
On te raccompagne.
Hold on a minute. Here's us at Mt. Rushmore.
Attends! Ca, c'était au mont Rushmore.
Do you remember, Truman, when Dad was still with us?
Papa était encore avec nous.
That was quite a drive. You slept the whole way there.
On a fait de la route. Tu as dormi tout le trajet.
It looks so small.
Ca paraît petit!
Things always do when you look back, darling.
Ca fait toujours ça avec le recul.
Look, Truman.
Regarde, Truman.
The happiest day of our lives. Look.
Le plus beau jour de notre vie!
Jean, Jodie, Joanne.
Jean, Jodie, Joanne.
Doesn't she look beautiful, Truman?
Elle était belle, hein?
She still does.
Elle l'est toujours.
And there's lots of pages left over for baby photos.
Il reste des pages pour les bébés.
I would like to hold a grandchild in my arms before I go.
J'aimerais avoir des petits-enfants avant de disparaître!
Angela, we really should be getting you home.
On vous raméne.
- I'll take her. - No. You stay, relax.
- J'y vais. - Non, reste. Détends-toi.
Enjoy yourself. Your favorite show will be coming on.
C'est l'heure de ton émission.
You sure?
Tu es sùre?
Besides, we have something to discuss.
Et nous avons à parler.
- A certain person's birthday. - I see.
- De l'anniversaire de quelqu'un. - Je vois.
And there'll be another episode of I Love Lucy same time tomorrow.
Suite de L'Extravagante Lucy demain à la méme heure.
But right now, it's time for Golden Oldies.
Et maintenant, le cinè-club.
Tonight, we present the enduring, much-loved classic,
Ce soir, un grand classique:
Show Me the Way to Go Home.
Le Chemin qui méne chez soi.
A hymn of praise to small-town life,
Un hymne à la vie de province qui nous apprend
where we learn that you don't have to leave home
qu'on peut voyager en restant chez soi
to discover what the world's all about, and that no one is poor who has friends.
et que nul n'est pauvre s'il a un ami.
Full of laughter and love, pain and sadness, but ultimately redemption,
Du rire, de l'amour, de la douleur, mais, finalement, le salut.
we share the trials and tribulations of the Abbott family.
Nous vivons les tribulations de la famille Abbott.
Note the touching performance of Ronald Brierly as Uncle Bunny.
Bouleversante interprêtation de Ronald Brierly.
That scene with the bowl of cherries is going to have you
La scéne du bol de cerises
splitting your sides with laughter all over again.
est à se tordre.
And there'll be tears, too, when David and Jennifer are reunited.
Et vous pleurerez aux retrouvailles de David et Jennifer.
But enough from me. Let's join the Abbotts in Camden village.
Mais assez parlé, réjoignons les Abbott à Camden village.
Thank you, sweetie.
Merci, chéri.
I need to talk to you, but let's go outside.
Il faut que je te parle. Mais dehors.
- Sweetie, I'd love to, but I'm really late. - What's your rush?
- J'aimerais mais je suis en retard. - Une urgence?
Surgery.
En chirurgie.
There was that elevator disaster downtown. It was on the news last night.
Un accident d'ascenseur. Ils l'ont dit aux infos.
This cable just snapped.
Le câble a lâché.
This elevator, it just plummeted down 10 flights.
La cabine a chuté, pleine d'honnétes travailleurs!
The non-union workers. Just monsters.
Monstrueux!
That building, it's right next door to where you work.
L'immeuble se trouve juste à côté de ton bureau.
Can you imagine if you had been in there?
Tu aurais pu y étre.
It's not even worth thinking about.
Je n'ose pas y penser!
Anyway, I have an amputation on one of the young women
On doit amputer une femme.
who was in that elevator. She's very young. It's very sad.
Trés jeune. C'est trés triste.
- Anyway, wish me luck. - I'll cross my fingers for you.
- Souhaite-moi bonne chance. - Je croiserai les doigts.
Excuse me. Hi. Excuse me. May I help you?
Pardon. Je peux vous renseigner?
Yes. I'm looking for my wife, Nurse Burbank. It's very important.
Je cherche ma femme, Meryl Burbank. C'est urgent.
I'm afraid that that's not possible. She's in pre-op.
Ce n'est pas possible. Elle est au bloc.
Sure. Okay, fine.
Bon. Vous pouvez
- Can you pass along a message? - I'll try.
- lui transmettre un message? - J'essaierai.
Can you tell her I had to go to Fiji, and that I'll call her when I get there?
Je pars pour les Fidji. Je l'appellerai de là-bas.
- When you get to Fiji? - You got it.
- Des Fidji? - C'est cela.
- Fine. I'll tell her. - Thank you so much.
- Bien. Je le lui dirai. - Merci beaucoup.
- Sorry. - It's okay.
- Pardon. - Ca va.
Here, let me help you with that.
Je vais vous aider.
He's here.
Il est là.
I know.
Je sais.
Scalpel.
Scalpel.
I'm now making my primary incision
Je pratique une premiére incision
just above the right knee.
au-dessus du genou droit.
Hold her.
Tenez-la.
Nicely done.
C'est trés réussi.
This isn't going to be pretty. Unless you're family...
Ca va pas étre beau à voir.
It's just beautiful. Beautiful job.
Trés beau travail.
I'll just let someone else tidy up here.
Quelqu'un d'autre peut nettoyer.
- I'm sorry to keep you. - That's okay.
- Pardon de vous avoir fait attendre. - Ca va.
- How can I help? - I would like to book a flight to Fiji.
- Vous désirez? - Un billet pour les Fidji.
When would you like to leave?
Pour quand?
Today.
Aujourd'hui.
I'm sorry. I don't have anything for at least a month.
Désolée. Je n'ai rien avant un mois.
- A month? - It's the busy season.
- Un mois? - C'est la pleine saison.
You want to book the flight?
Vous réservez?
It doesn't matter. I'll make other arrangements, okay?
Non, tant pis. Je vais faire autrement.
Last call for Chicago!
Les passagers pour Chicago,
All aboard!
embarquement immédiat!
Thank you.
Merci.
Windy city, here we come.
Chicago, à nous deux!
- Hi.
- Salut.
Hello. Hi.
Salut.
Sisters.
Mes soeurs.
- Mom, isn't that... - Face the front.
- Maman, c'est lui... - Regarde devant toi.
Everybody off. We've got a problem.
Tout le monde descend.
I'm sorry, son.
Désolé.
His father was from Chicago, wasn't he?
Son pére était pas de Chicago?
No. His dentist was from Pensacola. His father was from Des Moines.
Son dentiste est de Pensacola, son pére de Des Moines.
But how come he wants to go to Chicago?
Pourquoi il va à Chicago?
He's not going to Chicago. He's not going anywhere.
II ne va nulle part.
He has to have it out with Meryl.
Il faut qu'il s'explique avec Meryl.
Truman?
Truman?
- Honey, are you okay? - Get in.
- Ca va? - Monte.
Truman.
Truman.
Look.
Regarde.
What?
Quoi?
I predict that in just a moment,
Je prédis que dans un instant,
we will see a lady on a red bike, followed by a man with flowers
on verra passer une dame sur un vélo, un homme avec des fleurs,
and a Volkswagen Beetle with a dented fender.
puis une Coccinelle cabossée.
- Truman, please. - Look.
- Truman, s'il te plaît. - Regarde!
Lady,
La dame,
flowers,
les fleurs,
and...
et...
- Truman, this is silly. - There it is!
- C'est ridicule! - La voilà!
There's that dented Beetle! Yes!
La Coccinelle!
Don't you want to know how I did that? I'll tell you.
Je t'explique?
They're on a loop. They go around the block.
Lls tournent en boucle.
They come back. They go around again. They just go round and round.
Ils font le tour du pâté de maisons.
Round and round.
Ils tournent sans arrét!
I invited Rita and Marlon for a barbecue on Sunday.
J'ai invité Marlon et Rita pour un barbecue dimanche.
- I'm gonna make my potato salad. - I won't be here Sunday.
- Je vais faire une salade. - Je ne serai pas là.
I need you to remind me we need more charcoal.
Il faut acheter du charbon.
Are you listening to a word I'm saying?
Tu écoutes ce que je te dis?
You're upset because you want to go to Fiji. Is that it?
Tu veux aller aux Fidji, c'est ça?
Okay, go.
Vas-y.
I think you should save for a few months, and then go.
Economise pendant quelques mois et vas-y.
There. Are you happy now?
Tu es content?
I'm going to go take a shower.
Je vais me doucher.
Let's go now.
Partons.
I'm ready to go now. Why wait? Early bird gathers no moss.
On peut partir tout de suite.
Rolling stone catches the worm, right?
A pierre qui roule, rien d'impossible.
Truman, what are you doing?
Qu'est-ce que tu fais?
Truman!
Truman!
Where shall we go?
Où est-ce qu'on pourrait aller?
- Truman, where are we going? - I don't really know.
- Où va-t-on? - Je ne sais pas.
I guess I'm being spontaneous.
Je fais dans la spontanéité.
Somebody, help me! I'm being spontaneous!
Au secours! Je fais dans la spontanéité!
Forget Fiji.
Oublions les Fidji.
- Can't very well drive to Fiji, can we? - No.
- On peut pas y aller en voiture! - Non.
- What about Atlantic City? - No, you hate to gamble.
- Si on allait à Atlantic City? - Tu détestes le jeu.
- That's right, I do, don't I? - So why would you want to go there?
- C'est vrai. - Alors, pourquoi y aller?
Because I never have. That's why people go places, isn't it?
Parce que je ne connais pas. C'est pour ça que les gens voyagent.
- Truman, I think I'm going to throw up. - Me, too.
- Je vais vomir. - Moi aussi!
Blocked at every turn.
Coincé à chaque tournant!
Beautifully synchronized, don't you agree?
Belle synchronisation.
- You're blaming me for the traffic? - Should I?
- Tu m'accuses? - Je devrais?
Truman, let's go home.
Rentrons à la maison.
You're right. We could be stuck here for hours.
Tu as raison. Ca peut durer des heures.
It could be like this all the way to Atlantic City.
Ce sera comme ça jusqu'à Atlantic City.
Let's go back.
Rentrons.
I'm sorry. I don't know what got into me.
Pardon. Je ne sais pas ce qui m'a pris.
Can you please slow down?
Tu pourrais ralentir?
Yes, I can.
Je pourrais.
- Truman, that's our turnoff. - I changed my mind again.
- C'est notre rue! - J'ai changé d'avis.
What's New Orleans like this time of year? Mardi Gras!
Allons à la Nouvelle-Orléans. C'est mardi gras!
Look, Meryl, same road, no cars.
Regarde. Méme rue. Plus de voitures.
It's magic.
C'est magique!
Look, you let me out. You're not right in the head.
Dépose-moi! Tu n'es pas normal.
You want to destroy yourself, you do it on your own.
Tue-toi tout seul!
I think I'd like a little company.
J'aime autant à deux.
Truman, you knew this would happen.
Tu devais t'y attendre.
You know you can't drive over water.
Tu sais que tu ne supportes pas l'eau.
Let's go home where you'll feel safe.
Rentrons chez nous, à l'abri.
- Give me your hand. - Sweetie.
- Donne-moi la main. - Chéri.
Drive.
Conduis!
Truman!
Truman!
We shouldn't be doing this! Truman, we're breaking the law!
Nous sommes en infraction!
- Oh, my! - You can do it.
- Oh! - Tu peux le faire!
- Please, don't! - You can make it.
- Non! - On peut y arriver.
Truman.
Truman.
We're over.
On est passés!
- We're over the bridge. - We're over?
- On est passés! - On est de l'autre côté?
- We're over.
- On est passés. - On est de l'autre côté.
Truman, what about that sign?
Et le panneau?
I'm sure they're exaggerating. We'll be fine.
Lls exagérent.
Exaggerating? Do you believe that?
Et ça, alors?
- Truman, let's go back! - Can't go back!
- Truman, rentrons! - Impossible!
Oh, my! Truman, we're on fire!
Nous brùlons!
- It's okay. - We're on fire!
- Ca va. - Nous brùlons.
It's okay. It's just smoke.
C'est que de la fumée!
- You okay? - Yes.
- Ca va. - Oui.
- Want to do it again? - No!
- On remet ça? - Non.
Truman, stop! Oh, God!
Truman, arréte!
So what are we going to do for money when we get to New Orleans?
Comment ferons-nous, pour l'argent?
I have my Seahaven bank card.
J'ai ma carte de crédit.
So what? We're just gonna eat into our savings, is that it?
On va dépenser nos économies, c'est ça?
I'm going to have to call your mother when we get there.
J'appellerai ta mére.
She's going to be worried sick. I don't know how she's going to take this.
Elle en sera malade. J'ignore comment elle le prendra.
What now?
Quoi encore?
This is a red alert.
Etat d'alerte maximal.
Truman, it looks like a leak at the plant.
Il doit y avoir une fuite à la centrale.
Back up. Leak at the plant.
Demi-tour. Une fuite.
- We had to shut her down. - Is there any way around?
- La route est barrée. - Il y a une déviation?
- Whole area's being evacuated. - Is there anything I can do?
- Tout est bouclé. - Je peux étre utile?
- No, ma'am. - Thank you for your help.
- Non, madame. - Merci.
You're welcome, Truman.
De rien, Truman.
Truman.
Truman.
Truman, come back!
Reviens!
Stop him!
Arrétez-le!
Truman!
Truman!
Catch him on the left!
Attrapez-le!
Stay away!
N'approchez pas!
No.
Non.
...now in custody.
...en détention prêventive.
Thank you both so much for your help. I really appreciate it.
Je vous suis trés reconnaissante.
He's lucky to be alive, ma'am. Next time, we'll have to file charges.
Il a eu de la chance. La prochaine fois, on l'inculpe.
I understand.
Je comprends.
- Thanks again. - Good night.
- Merci encore. - Bonne nuit.
Let me get you some help, Truman.
Je voudrais t'aider.
You're not well.
Tu n'es pas bien.
Why do you want to have a baby with me?
Pourquoi veux-tu un enfant de moi?
You can't stand me.
Tu ne me supportes pas.
That's not true.
Ce n'est pas vrai!
Why don't you let me fix you some of this new Mococoa drink?
Je vais te préparer un bol de Mococoa,
All natural cocoa beans from the upper slopes of Mt. Nicaragua.
le cacao du Nicaragua,
No artificial sweeteners.
sans édulcorant de synthése.
What the hell are you talking about?
Qu'est-ce que tu racontes?
Who are you talking to?
A qui tu parles?
I've tasted other cocoas. This is the best.
C'est le meilleur des cacaos.
What the hell does this have to do with anything?
Qu'est-ce que ça vient faire là?
Tell me what's happening!
Dis-moi ce qui se passe!
You're having a nervous breakdown, that's what's happening.
Tu fais une dépression nerveuse.
You're part of this, aren't you?
Tu es dans le coup?
- Truman. - Meryl!
- Truman. - Meryl!
You are scaring me.
Tu me fais peur!
No. You're scaring me, Meryl.
Non. C'est toi qui me fais peur.
What are you going to do? Dice me? Slice me and peel me?
Que vas-tu faire? Me couper en dés, en tranches, ou m'éplucher?
There are so many choices!
Tu as l'embarras du choix!
Do something!
Faites quelque chose!
What?
Quoi?
What did you say?
Que dis-tu?
- Who were you talking to? - Nothing. I didn't say anything.
- A qui parles-tu? - Je n'ai rien dit.
I didn't say anything.
Je n'ai rien dit.
- You said "do something." - No, I didn't. I wasn't talking to anybody.
- Si! - Non. Je n'ai parlé à personne.
- Talk to me! - I don't know anything. Please stop.
- Dis-moi tout! - Je ne sais rien!
Stay where you are.
Ne bouge pas.
Truman?
Truman?
Truman.
Truman.
Oh, thank God!
Dieu soit loué!
How can anyone expect me to carry on under these conditions?
Comment veut-on que je continue dans ces conditions?
It's unprofessional.
Ce n'est pas professionnel!
It's okay.
Ca va aller.
Everything's going to be okay. It's all gonna be fine.
Ca va s'arranger.
I don't know what to think, Marlon.
Je ne sais plus quoi penser, Marlon.
Maybe I'm losing my mind, but...
Je perds peut-étre la téte mais...
It feels like the whole world revolves around me somehow.
J'ai l'impression que le monde repose sur moi.
That's a lot of world for one man, Truman.
C'est beaucoup pour un seul homme.
Sure that's not wishful thinking?
Tu ne fantasmes pas?
You wishing you'd made something more out of yourself?
Tu es peut-étre déçu de ton sort.
Come on, who hasn't sat in the john,
Qui n'a pas révé, sur le trône,
had an imaginary interview on Seahaven Tonight?
qu'il était interviewé à la télé?
- Who hasn't wanted to be somebody? - This is different.
- On veut tous réussir. - C'est pas ça.
Everybody seems to be in on it.
Tout le monde a l'air de méche.
I've been your best friend since we were 7 years old, Truman.
Je suis ton meilleur ami depuis l'âge de sept ans.
The only way you and I ever made it through school
A l'école, on a toujours copié
was by cheating off each other's test papers.
l'un sur l'autre.
Jesus, they were identical.
Mot pour mot!
But I always felt safe knowing that.
Moi, ça me rassurait.
'Cause whatever the answer was, we were right together,
Quelle que soit la réponse, on avait raison ensemble.
and we were wrong together.
Ou on se trompait ensemble.
Remember that time I stayed up with you all night in your tent
Tu te rappelles cette nuit dans ta tente,
because you wanted to play North Pole?
à jouer au pôle Nord?
And I got pneumonia?
Et ma pneumonie?
You remember that?
Tu te souviens?
You were out of school for about a month.
Tu as été absent pendant un mois!
You're the closest thing I ever had to a brother, Truman.
Tu ressembles au frére que je n'ai pas eu.
I know that things
Je sais que
haven't really worked out for either of us like we used to dream they would.
tout n'a pas marché comme nous en révions.
I know that feeling, when it's like everything's slipping away
Je connais ce sentiment que tout nous échappe,
and you don't want to believe it,
ce refus d'y croire qui pousse
so you look for answers somewhere else, but...
à chercher ailleurs, mais...
The point is,
Mais,
I'd gladly walk in front of traffic for you.
je me précipiterais sous une voiture pour toi.
The point is, I would gladly step in front of traffic for you, Truman.
Je me prêcipiterais sous une voiture pour toi, Truman.
And the last thing I'd ever do is lie to you.
Et jamais je ne te mentirais.
And the last thing that I would ever do
Et jamais
I mean, think about it, Truman.
Rends-toi compte.
If everybody is in on it,
Si tout le monde est de méche,
I'd have to be in on it, too.
alors moi aussi.
I'm not in on it, Truman, because
Je ne suis pas de méche, Truman.
there is no "it."
Il n'y a pas de méche.
You were right about one thing, though.
Mais tu as raison sur un point.
What's that?
Lequel?
The thing that started all this.
Ce qui a déclenché tout ça.
Yep. I found him for you, Truman.
Je te l'ai retrouvé.
That's why I came by tonight.
Je venais te le dire.
I'm sure he's got quite a story to tell.
Il a des choses à te raconter!
Go to him.
Va le retrouver.
Easy on the fog.
Moins de brouillard.
Stand by, crane cam.
La grue se tient préte.
Crane cam.
La grue.
Button cam 3.
Caméra-bouton 3.
I never stopped believing.
Je n'ai jamais cessé d'y croire.
And wide, curb cam 8.
Plan large. Caméra-trottoir 8.
My son.
Mon fils!
- Move in for a close-up? - No.
- Gros plan? - Non.
Move back
Recule.
and fade up music.
Musique.
And now go in close.
Maintenant, on resserre.
All those years wasted.
Toutes ces années perdues!
I'll make it up to you, son. I swear.
On les rattrapera. Je te le jure.
Dad.
Papa!
Yes!
Oui!
Bravo.
Bravo.
That will win the ratings period.
On va faire exploser l'audimat.
Congratulations.
Félicitations.
Okay, everybody, quiet down. Let's concentrate.
On se calme. On reste concentrés.
- Great television. - That was good work.
- Un grand moment de télévision. - Beau travail.
Let's get some champagne up here.
Champagne!
Congratulations.
Félicitations.
- Well done, Christof. - It was brilliant. It just broke my heart.
- Magnifique, Christof! - Bouleversant!
- Well done, everyone! - Bravo!
- Bravo à tous! - Bravo!
Congratulations.
Félicitations.
1.7 billion were there for his birth.
1,7 milliard de spectateurs l'ont vu naître.
The world stood still forth at stolen kiss.
Le monde a retenu son souffle pour ce baiser volé.
And as he grew, so did the technology.
Et la technique a grandi avec lui.
An entire human life
La vie d'un homme...
recorded on an intricate network of hidden cameras
diffusée en direct et sans montage,
and broadcast live and unedited, 24 hours a day,
24 heures sur 24,
seven days a week, to an audience around the globe.
7 jours sur 7, dans le monde entier.
Coming to you now from Seahaven island,
Depuis Seahaven lsland,
enclosed in the largest studio ever constructed,
dans le plus grand studio jamais conçu,
and along with the Great Wall of China,
qui est, avec la Muraille de Chine,
one of only two manmade structures visible from space,
la seule construction humaine visible de l'espace,
now in its 30th great year,
pour la 30e année,
it's The Truman Show.
c'est ie Truman Show.
What a week it's been. I don't know about you,
Quelle semaine!
I was on pins and needles the entire time.
J'étais sur des charbons ardents.
Hello and good evening. I'm your host Mike Michaelson,
Bonsoir. Mike Michaelson pour vous servir.
and welcome to Trutalk.
Bienvenue à Le moment de vérité,
Our forum for issues growing out of the show.
notre forum sur le Truman Show.
But tonight, something very special indeed.
Ce soir, un événement:
A rare and exclusive interview with the show's conceiver and creator.
Un entretien exclusif avec le créateur du Show.
So come with us now as we go live to the lunar room
Alors, suivez-nous
on the 221st floor of the Omni-cam ecosphere.
dans la rêgie lunaire au 221e niveau de l'êcosphère Omnicam.
That's where we'll find the world's greatest tele-visionary.
Nous y retrouverons le plus grand télévisionnaire,
The designer and architect of the world within a world
le concepteur de ce monde dans le monde,
that is Seahaven Island: Christof
Christof.
Before we begin, I'd like to thank you on behalf of our audience,
Tout d'abord,
for granting this exclusive interview.
merci de nous accorder cet entretien.
We know how demanding your schedule is
On sait que votre temps est prêcieux
and we all know how jealously you guard your privacy.
et que vous veillez jalousement sur votre vie privée.
This, sir, is indeed an honor.
C'est pour nous un honneur.
Don't mention it.
Je vous en prie.
The catalyst for the recent dramatic events on the show
Le catalyseur des rêcents événements a été
has been Truman's father, Kirk,
le pére de Truman,
and his attempts to infiltrate the show. But before we get into that,
qui a voulu infiltrer le Show.
I think it's worth noting this is not the first time
Mais ce n'est pas la premiére fois
someone from the outside has attempted to reach Truman, is it?
qu'un élément extérieur tente d'atteindre Truman.
We have had our close calls in the past.
Il y a eu des prêcédents.
Truman! It's television! Yes!
Truman! C'est de la télé!
Yes! I did it! I'm on The Truman Show!
Je l'ai fait! Je suis dans le Truman Show.
But there's never been anything to compare with
Mais rien de comparable
this most recent breach in security.
avec ce qui vient de se passer:
The first intruder to be a former cast member.
L'intrus est un ancien protagoniste.
A dead one at that.
Mort, en l'occurrence.
Got to say, writing Kirk back in, masterstroke.
Réintégrer Kirk fut un coup de maître.
Since Kirk started this whole crisis in Truman's life,
Il avait déclenché cette crise:
I came to the conclusion that he was the only one who could end it.
J'ai décidé qu'il pouvait y mettre un terme.
Truman!
Truman!
Truman, no!
Truman, non!
That's off-limits.
C'est interdit!
- Why? What's over there? - Nothing. It's dangerous. That's all.
- Pourquoi? - C'est dangereux!
You've got to know your limitations, Truman.
II faut respecter les limites.
But let's remind viewers of exactly why Dad was written out in the first place.
Rappelons pourquoi papa avait disparu du scénario.
As Truman grew up, we were forced to manufacture ways
Truman grandissant, il fallait trouver
to keep him on the island.
des moyens de le retenir sur l'île.
I'd like to be an explorer, like the great Magellan.
Je veux étre explorateur, comme Magellan.
You're too late.
Trop tard.
There's really nothing left to explore.
Il n'y a plus rien à découvrir.
Finally, I came up with the concept of Kirk's drowning.
J'ai eu l'idée de la noyade de Kirk.
Most effective. Truman's been terrified of the water ever since.
Depuis, Truman est terrifié par l'eau.
When Kirk read the synopsis for the Death At Sea episode,
Lorsque Kirk a lu la scéne de la noyade,
he was disappointed, to say the least.
il a été extrêmement déçu.
I'm sure that's what caused him to break back onto the set.
Il a donc voulu revenir de force.
But how do you intend to explain his 22-year absence?
Comment justifierez-vous son absence de 22 ans?
- Amnesia. - Brilliant.
- L'amnésie. - Gênial!
Let's take some viewer phone calls.
Prenons un appel
Charlotte, North Carolina, you're on with Christof
de Charlotte, en Caroline du Nord. C'est à vous.
Yeah, hi, Christof
Bonjour, Christof.
I was just wondering how many cameras you got there in that town.
Combien de camêras avez-vous?
Somewhere in the vicinity of 5,000.
Dans les 5000.
-That's a lot of cameras. - Remember, we started with just one.
- C'est beaucoup! - A l'origine, il n'y en avait qu'une.
He was curious from birth.
Il s'est distingué dés sa naissance,
Premature by two weeks. It was almost as if he couldn't wait to get started.
prêmaturêe de quinze jours, comme s'il était pressé.
And his eagerness to leave his mother's womb
Et c'est cette impatience à voir le jour
was the very reason he was the one who was selected.
qui explique qu'il a été choisi.
In competition with five other unwanted pregnancies,
Parmi six naissances non désirêes.
the casting of a show, determined by an air date,
La programmation a déterminé le choix.
Truman was the one who arrived on cue.
Truman est arrivé à l'heure.
Incidentally, I believe Truman is the first child
C'êtait le premier enfant
to have been legally adopted by a corporation.
adopté par une production?
That's correct.
C'est exact.
The show has generated enormous revenues,
Le Show a gênêrê d'ênormes bênêfices.
now equivalent to the gross national product of a small country.
L'équivalent du P.N.B. D'un petit pays.
People forget it takes
Notre équipe
the population of an entire country to keep the show running.
équivaut à la population d'un pays.
Since the show is on 24 hours a day without commercial interruption,
Vous n'avez pas d'interruptions publicitaires.
all those staggering revenues are generated by product placement.
Ces bênêfices viennent donc des produits dérivés.
That's true. Everything on the show is for sale.
Exact. Tout est à vendre.
From the actors' wardrobe, food products, to the very homes they live in.
Les costumes, les produits, les maisons.
All of it available in the Truman catalog
Le tout disponible sur catalogue.
and operators are standing by.
Le standard est ouvert.
Christof, let me ask you.
Une question:
Why do you think that Truman has never come close
Pourquoi Truman n'a-t-il jamais découvert
to discovering the true nature of his world until now?
la vraie nature du monde qui l'entoure?
We accept the reality of the world with which we are presented.
Chacun accepte la rêalitê du monde auquel il est confronté.
It's as simple as that.
C'est aussi simple que ça.
The Hague for Christof
Un appel de La Hague.
Hello? The Hague?
Allô?
All right, we've lost that call. Let's go to Hollywood. You're on Trutalk.
On l'a perdu. Allons à Hollywood.
Hi, I'd just like to say one thing.
Je n'ai qu'une chose à dire...
You're a liar and a manipulator.
Vous étes un menteur.
And what you've done to Truman is sick.
Tout ça est monstrueux!
We remember this voice, don't we?
On connaît cette voix.
-How could we forget? - Let's go to another call.
- Comment l'oublier? - Prenons un autre appel.
No. It's fine, Mike.
Non, laissez, Mike.
I love to reminisce with former members of the cast.
J'aime évoquer le passé avec les anciens personnages.
Sylvia,
Sylvia,
as you announced so melodramatically to the world,
avec votre sens du mèlodrame,
you think because you batted your eyes at Truman once,
vous croyez, parce que vous avez échangé des regards,
flirted with him,
flirtè avec lui,
stole a few minutes of air time with him
volant quelques minutes d'antenne
to thrust yourself and your politics into the limelight,
pour diffuser votre message politique,
that you know him? That you know what's right for him?
vous croyez le connaître? Savoir ce qui lui convient?
You really think you're in a position to judge him?
Etes-vous bien placêe pour juger?
What right do you have to take a baby
De quel droit avez-vous pris un enfant
and turn his life into some kind of mockery?
pour faire de sa vie une bouffonnerie?
Don't you ever feel guilty?
Vous ne vous sentez jamais coupable?
I have given Truman a chance to lead a normal life.
J'ai offert à Truman une vie normale.
The world, the place you live in,
C'est le monde dans lequel vous vivez
is the sick place.
qui est monstrueux.
Seahaven is the way the world should be.
Seahaven est un monde idêal.
He's not a performer. He's a prisoner. Look at what you've done to him!
Il est prisonnier! Voyez ce que vous lui avez fait!
He could leave at any time.
II est libre de partir,
If his was more than just a vague ambition,
si c'est plus qu'un vague désir.
if he was absolutely determined to discover the truth,
S'il était déterminé à connaître la vérité,
there's no way we could prevent him.
on ne pourrait l'en empécher.
I think what distresses you,
Ce qui vous dêsole,
really, caller, is that ultimately
en rêalité, c'est qu'en fin de compte,
Truman prefers his cell, as you call it.
il prêfère sa prison, comme vous l'appelez.
That's where you're wrong.
Vous vous trompez.
You're so wrong, and he'll prove you wrong.
Lourdement! Et il vous donnera tort.
Aside from the heated comments of a very vocal minority,
Si l'on excepte ces critiques d'une minorité tapageuse,
it's been an overwhelmingly positive experience.
on peut dire que l'expérience est très positive.
Yes. For Truman and for the viewing public.
Pour Truman et pour le public.
Christof, I can't thank you enough
Encore merci
forgiving so generously of your time tonight.
de nous avoir accordé tant de temps.
I think it's safe to say that now that this crisis is behind us
Maintenant que la crise est passée
and that Truman's back to his old self,
et que Truman s'est ressaisi,
we can look forward to some exciting new developments.
de nouvelles péripéties sont à espérer.
Mike, the big news is that Meryl will be leaving Truman
La grande nouvelle, c'est que Meryl quittera Truman
in an upcoming episode.
dans un prochain épisode.
And a new romantic interest will be introduced.
Un nouvel amour va naître.
I'm determined that television's first on-air conception will still take place.
La premiére grossesse en direct aura lieu.
Another television milestone straight ahead. You heard it here first.
Une nouvelle étape de l'histoire de la télévision!
It has been a singular honor and a pleasure, sir.
Vous en étes les premiers informés. C'est un honneur.
-Christof, thank you. - Thank you, Mike.
- Merci, Christof. - Merci, Mike.
- Simeon. - What?
- Simeon. - Quoi?
Is he looking at us?
II nous regarde?
Jesus, do you think he knows?
Pensez-vous qu'il sache?
Hello?
Allô?
Better call Christof.
J'appelle Christof.
Hello? Come in, Major Burbank.
Répondez, Major Burbank.
Jesus.
Mon Dieu!
- He's back to his old self. - Thank God.
- Il est redevenu lui-méme! - Dieu merci.
That's an unusual cat, my man.
C'est vraiment un drôle d'oiseau!
I hereby pro claim this planet...
Je baptise cette planéte
Trumania of the Burbank galaxy.
Trumania de la galaxie Burbank.
- Is he gonna go? - Okay, hallway camera ready.
- Il va sortir? - Caméra-couloir en place.
That one's for free.
C'êtait gratuit.
Keep up with him, 'cause he'll move fast.
Restez sur lui.
Stand by, all house cameras.
Tenez-vous préts.
- Morning! - Good morning.
- Bonjour! - Bonjour.
In case I don't see you...
Et si je ne vous revois pas.
Good afternoon, good evening, and good night.
Une bonne soirée et une excellente nuit!
- Good afternoon... - Good morning.
- Bonne soirée... - Bonjour.
...evening and good night.
...une excellente nuit!
- Morning, Truman. - Morning, Spencer.
- Bonjour, Truman. - Bonjour, Spencer.
- How's it going? - Let me check.
- Ca va? - Je vérifie.
Vital signs are good.
La tension est excellente!
Pluto!
Pluto!
Good morning, Truman.
Bonjour, Truman.
- Look who's here. - Beautiful day, isn't it?
- Ca par exemple! - Belle journée!
Every single day.
Toujours.
The policy, we've thought about it and we're gonna take it.
Pour l'assurance, on est décidés.
- You're kidding? - No!
- Sans blague? - Non!
Why don't we go up to my office right now and we'll sign the papers?
Vous venez signer?
Next week would be much better.
La semaine prochaine.
- All right. See you guys. - Okay, bye now. See you next week.
- Je compte sur vous! - A la semaine prochaine.
- Give me something to look forward to. - You got it.
- En voilà une bonne nouvelle. - Et comment!
See, this isn't about insurance.
II ne s'agit pas d'assurance,
This is about the great variable: when will death occur?
mais de la grande inconnue: Quand la mort surviendra-t-elle?
Could be a week, a month, a year.
Dans une semaine, un mois, un an.
Could be today.
Aujourd'hui!
"Sunbather, minding his own business,
Vous prenez un bain de soleil,
"stabbed in the heart by the tip of a runaway beach umbrella."
un parasol vient vous transpercer le coeur.
No way to guard against that kind of thing.
Nul n'est à l'abri.
Sorry, excuse me.
Un moment, s'il vous plaît.
Truman, this is Vivien. Vivien, this is Truman.
Truman, Vivien. Vivien, Truman.
The two of you are gonna be neighbors.
Vous allez étre voisins.
I guess what I'm saying is that life is
Ce que je veux dire c'est que la vie est
fragile.
fragile.
- Vivien, your office. - Sorry.
- Vivien, votre bureau. - Pardon.
What's that? I'm sorry.
Quoi? Pardon!
You do?
Oui?
Great. Let me take your information.
Formidable. Je note vos coordonnées.
Ready, 2. Go to 2.
Caméra 2.
And back to medium.
Plan moyen.
And wide.
Général.
I was just trying to train the kid to...
J'apprenais au jeune à...
Never mind.
Peu importe.
What's he doing in the basement?
Que fait-il à la cave?
He moved down there after Meryl packed up and left.
II y est depuis le départ de Meryl.
Why wasn't I told?
On ne m'a pas prévenu?
Any unpredictable behavior has to be reported.
Tout comportement anormal doit m'étre signalé.
He's just sleeping, I thought.
Il dort. J'ai pensé que...
- This the best shot we've got? - What's to see?
- C'est le meilleur angle? - Pour voir quoi?
- What's on the clock cam? - It's an obstruction.
- La caméra dans la pendule? - Elle est bouchée.
- What happened down there? - He was just tidying up his garbage.
- Que s'est-il passé? - Il faisait du rangement.
I was gonna call you, but halfway through, he gave up, and he fell asleep.
J'allais vous avertir quand il s'est endormi.
I wanna check on the setups for the insurance convention tomorrow.
Répétons pour la convention de demain.
- Yes. - Yeah.
- Oui.
Nice move.
On s'en sort bien.
There you go.
Voilà.
Isolate the audio.
Donnez-moi tout le son.
Give me a close-up on his torso.
Resserrez sur lui.
He's still breathing.
Il respire encore.
Where's Chloe? Call him.
Chloe. Appelez-le.
- What do you want me to say? - Tell him it's a wrong number.
- Qu'est-ce que je dis? - Dites que c'est une erreur.
What took you so long?
T'en as mis un temps!
Just had to wait for it. They were busy.
J'ai fait la queue. Ils étaient débordés.
Here. What's going on?
Il se passe quoi?
I don't know. They're...
Je sais pas.
He came down into the room. He did nothing but stand around for a while.
Il est resté debout à ne rien faire.
Shut up and watch it.
Fermez-la et regardez.
Then we went to night vision.
Puis on est passé en mode nuit.
He's asleep.
Il dort.
- There! - What?
- Là! - Quoi?
- Zoom in. - On which?
- Zoomez. - Sur quoi?
Under the chair there.
Sous la chaise!
Enhance it.
Faites le point.
- Is it... - My God.
- Il n'est pas sorti... - Mon Dieu.
He couldn't have gone up the stairs. He must still be in the room.
Il doit étre là.
- Get Marlon over there. - Right away.
- Envoyez Marlon. - Vite.
Truman!
Truman!
Surprise party!
Surprise!
Come on, buddy.
Allez, mec.
I got a six-pack of cold brewskis with our name on them.
J'ai six bibines bien fraîches à nos noms!
Come on, pal. Come on, buddy.
Montre-toi.
Shit.
Merde!
Marlon, find him. He's still in the room.
Trouvez-le. Il est encore là.
Come out, come out, wherever you are.
Allez, montre-toi.
That's good. Keep it light.
Bien. Léger.
I know you're in here. I'm gonna find you.
Je sais que tu es là.
Check under the table.
Sous la table.
The closet, behind you.
Le placard, derriére vous.
Huh.
Hein.
Gee.
Bon sang.
I wonder where he could possibly be.
Je me demande où il peut étre.
The lawn cam, get me the lawn cam.
Caméra jardin!
Don't look in the camera. Say something. Keep it going.
Ne regardez pas la caméra! Enchaînez!
He's gone.
II a disparu.
- Cut transmission! - Cut transmission?
- Coupez! - La retransmission?
Cut it!
Coupez!
Jesus! God in heaven!
Oh, mon Dieu!
- Everything's black. - Give me the phone.
- Il n'y a plus rien. - Passe-moi le téléphone.
I don't know where he is, but he's gone.
Je ne sais pas où il est, mais il est disparu.
All right. We've got every available extra looking for him.
Tous les figurants sont mobilisés.
The principals are helping out. The crew, too. So every sector's covered.
Les acteurs, les techniciens. On fouille partout.
- What about prop cars? - Yes, they've been accounted for.
- Les véhicules? - Aucun ne manque.
He has to be on foot.
Il est sùrement à pied.
He has the world's most recognizable face. He can't disappear.
Il est connu, il ne peut pas passer inaperçu.
Go.
Allez.
Hunt him. Yeah. Go find him, Pluto.
Cherche, Pluto!
Good dog!
Bon chien!
All this fuss.
Quel tintouin!
If he could just hear my voice.
Si seulement il m'entendait!
Truman!
Truman!
Let me try. Truman!
Je vais essayer.
It's me, Dad!
C'est moi, Papa!
Let's talk.
Parlons-nous!
Yeah, I know.
Oui, je sais.
Just about done with the square.
On a presque fini.
Got to go back to Barrymore, check the interiors.
Il faut retourner chez Barrymore.
- He's got to be in there. - Barrymore.
- Il y est sùrement. - Barrymore?
But what about the college? Who's watching that?
Et l'école? Qui s'en charge?
I don't know.
Je ne sais pas.
- Send somebody over there, okay? - All right.
- Envoyez quelqu'un. - D'accord.
Take another man and get down there now, all right?
Allez-y avec quelqu'un.
I don't give a damn. Just find the son of a bitch.
Retrouvez ce salopard!
Get some batteries.
Prenez des lampes.
This guy's not gonna glow in the dark. Get them down here.
Il n'est pas phosphorescent!
I don't know what's going on. Reroute it back to me.
Je ne sais pas ce qui se passe.
We need more light. We'll never find him this way.
Sans lumiére, on ne le trouvera jamais.
What time is it?
Quelle heure est-il?
It's way too early for that.
Beaucoup trop tôt pour ça.
Cue the sun.
Envoyez le soleil.
What time is it?
Il est quelle heure?
Christof, what's going on?
Que se passe-t-il?
Did you know there's a rumor circulating that he's dead?
Le bruit court déjà qu'il est mort.
You hear me?
Vous m'entendez?
The media is having a feeding frenzy over this.
Les médias sont sur les dents.
All the phone lines are jammed,
Le standard explose.
and every network has a pirated shot
Toutes les chaînes diffusent
of Marlon making an ass of himself in front of the camera.
la gaffe de Marlon.
The sponsors are threatening to rip up their contracts.
Nos annonceurs menacent de mettre fin aux contrats.
Why? We're getting higher ratings with this graphic
Pourquoi? Ce déroulant
than we've ever had on this show.
bat tous les records d'audience.
No sign of him.
Rien.
Marlon, why don't you head back to town and join the others?
Bien. Réjoins les autres en ville.
Everyone else is at first positions, okay? Thank you.
Tout le monde est déjà en place.
Everyone's at first positions, right?
Tout le monde est en place?
We've got the light. So he's got to be there somewhere.
II doit bien étre quelque part.
We're not watching the sea.
On ne surveille pas la mer.
Hang on a minute. Why would we watch the sea?
Pour quoi faire?
Sweep the harbor.
Balayez le port.
Bring up the harbor cameras.
Connectez le port.
Shift all harbor cameras to computer, please.
Toutes les caméras du port.
Some of those are out, aren't they?
Certaines sont débranchées?
Yeah. We have four of them down, but we have the lighthouse cameras up.
Quatre sont H.S. Celles du phare fonctionnent.
- All buoy cams, please. - What's happening?
- Celles sur le large. - Que se passe-t-il?
Long-lens, shore-based cameras.
La plus longue focale.
- Why are we looking at the water? - Good.
- Pourquoi on regarde la mer? - Bien.
Pan and zoom please.
Zoome.
Truman,
Truman.
where are you going?
Où vas-tu?
How can he sail? He's in insurance.
II sait naviguer?
- Isn't he terrified of the water? - Resume transmission.
- Il supporte l'eau? - Reprenez l'antenne.
Resuming transmission.
Reprenez l'antenne.
- I got 2-to-1 he doesn't make it. - I want a piece of that.
- Deux contre un qu'il reste. - Je suis partant.
2-to-1 he doesn't make it.
Deux contre un qu'il reste.
Just leave them in the car.
Laissez les clés dessus!
Let's get off this mast shot. We can't see his face. Go to the cabin cam.
Changez de caméra, qu'on voie son visage.
There. Perfect.
Voilà. Parfait.
That's our hero shot.
Le héros.
Let's get another boat out there.
Envoyez un bateau.
Okay. Listen, Gus, I need you to talk to the guys on the ferry.
Passez-moi le ferry.
Come on. Get it moving. Get it out of here.
Larguez les amarres.
Come on.
Allez.
- I'm usually the bus driver. - Bottom line is they can't drive the boat.
- Je conduis le bus. - Ils savent pas naviguer.
They're actors.
C'est des acteurs!
How do we stop him?
On fait quoi?
Okay.
Bon.
We're going to be accessing the weather program now.
On va passer en mode météo.
So hold onto your hats. You got that?
Ca risque de décoiffer. Compris?
No. I think we're gonna want to localize the storm over the boat.
Non, je pense qu'on va circonscrire l'orage sur le bateau.
You can get the coordinates for that.
Entrez les données.
There's no rescue boat. He won't know what to do.
Il n'a pas de canot de sauvetage.
He'll turn back. He'll be too afraid.
Il fera demi-tour. Il aura trop peur.
Thar she blows.
C'est parti.
Come on.
Allez.
Give me some lightning.
Foudre.
Again.
Encore.
Hit him again!
Encore!
For God's sake, the whole world is watching.
Le monde entier regarde ça.
We can't let him die in front of a live audience.
Il ne va pas mourir en direct!
He was born in front of a live audience.
II est né en direct.
Come on, Truman!
Vas-y!
You can do it! Hold on!
Accroche-toi!
Is that the best you can do?
C'est tout ce que vous pouvez faire?
You're gonna have to kill me!
II faudra me tuer!
What shall we do with a drunken sailor?
Que peut-on faire d'un marin ivre?
- I demand that you cease transmission. - Keep running.
- Interrompez la retransmission. - Continuez.
What shall we do with a drunken sailor Early in the mornin'?
Que peut-on faire d'un marin ivre Au petit matin?
Increase the wind.
Plus de vent.
- I'm telling you for the last time. - How close is he?
- Plus de vent! - Il y est?
- Very close. - Capsize him. Tip him over.
- Presque. - Qu'il chavire.
- Damn you, Christof! - You can't. He's tied himself to the boat!
- Non, Christof! - Il s'est attaché au bateau!
Shut up!
Silence!
He's gonna drown, and he doesn't even care.
II va se noyer.
- Do it. - No.
- Faites-le! - Non.
Do it!
Faites-le!
That's enough.
Assez.
I want to talk to him.
Je vais lui parler.
Truman.
Truman.
You can speak.
Tu peux parler.
I can hear you.
Je t'entends.
Who are you?
Qui étes-vous?
I am the creator of a television show
Le créateur d'une émission de télévision
that gives hope and joy and inspiration to millions.
qui apporte joie et inspiration à des millions de gens.
Then who am I?
Et moi, qui suis-je?
You're the star.
Tu es le héros.
Was nothing real?
Rien n'était vrai?
You were real.
Toi, tu étais vrai.
That's what made you so good to watch.
C'est pour ça que tu étais si bon.
Listen to me, Truman.
Ecoute-moi.
There's no more truth out there
Il n'y a pas plus de vérité ici
than there is in the world I created for you.
que dans le monde que j'ai créé pour toi.
The same lies,
Mémes mensonges,
the same deceit.
méme supercherie.
But in my world
Mais, dans mon monde,
you have nothing to fear.
tu n'as rien à craindre.
I know you better than you know yourself
Je te connais mieux que toi-méme.
You never had a camera in my head.
Il n'y a pas de caméra dans ma téte!
You're afraid.
Tu as peur.
That's why you can't leave.
Tu ne peux pas partir.
It's okay, Truman.
Ce n'est pas grave.
I understand.
Je comprends.
I have been watching you your whole life.
J'ai suivi toute ta vie.
I was watching when you were born.
Je t'ai vu naître,
I was watching when you took your first step.
faire tes premiers pas.
I watched you on your first day of school.
J'étais là quand tu es entrê à l'école,
The episode when you lost your first tooth.
quand tu as perdu ta premiére dent.
You can't leave, Truman.
Tu ne peux pas partir.
Please, God.
Allez.
You belong here...
Ta place est ici...
You can do it.
Tu peux le faire!
...with me.
...avec moi.
Talk to me.
Parle-moi.
Say something.
Dis quelque chose.
Say something, God damn it. You're on television.
Parle, bon sang! Tu es à la télévision!
You're live to the whole world.
En direct dans le monde entier!
In case I don't see you,
Si je ne vous revois pas,
good afternoon, good evening, and good night.
une bonne soirée et une excellente nuit!
Yeah.
Eh oui!
Yeah!
Waw!
- He made it! Yeah! - All right, Truman!
- Il l'a fait! - Bravo, Truman!
- Cease transmission. - Ceasing transmission.
- Rendez l'antenne. - On rend l'antenne.
- You want another slice? - No. I'm okay.
- Une autre tranche? - Non merci.
What else is on? Where's the TV Guide?
On change? Où est le programme?